Out here in the Wild West,
cowboys herd cattle, rope calves,
ride bulls, and survive shootouts at high
noon. But in analytics, we wrangle data.
Instead of herding cattle, we herd messy
spreadsheets and inconsistent databases.
Instead of calf roping,
we rope in missing
values before they
escape into dashboards.
Instead of bull riding,
we hang on for dear
life while cleaning
chaotic real-world data.
And instead of shootouts
at high noon, we battle
duplicates, null value,
and corrupted records.
Welcome to the frontier
of SQL Data Wrangling.
300,
project on data wrangling.
For this particular project,
you're going to go in and transform
existing data to make it more
appropriate for analysis.
Data tends to be messy.
We bring it in from
different sources, and
it can be inconsistent.
We can have missing spaces. we can
have capitalization, spacing problems,
we can have missing or duplicate
data. Somebody could type in the
state Utah with four letters. They
could also type in UT. Some of
that UT is capitalized, some of
it's not. So that's the purpose of
today's project with data wrangling.
And this is a list of some of the
topics that we will be covering as
you work through the project today.
I've had a couple of students that
are now in the workforce check out
this project on data wrangling.
And one of the things that was
consistently mentioned as missing are
the use of temp tables when you're
wrangling data. So I'm going to briefly
introduce temp tables to get you
started on your project. A temp
table is just a short-lived table you
create inside a single session. You
can select, join, update, do all
sorts of things with it. We can run
this temp table, We'll manipulate,
change, update, wrangle the data,
and then when it looks good, we
can put it back into the original
table. If we make mistakes in a temp
table, no harm, no foul, we can
drop that temp table and start over.
In other classes, you'll spend
a lot of time on ETL, extract,
transform, and load, but for
our data wrangling project, when
we're using temp tables, we
effectively are doing ETL. And I'm
going to show you an example of
how this extract, transform, and
load would take place. Initially,
we're going to extract the
data. In our case, we're going to
extract from an existing table.
Once we extract that data,
we put it into a temp table,
and then we can transform it,
manipulate it, make changes.
And then once we're happy with
those changes, we can load it
into either a new table or the
original table that we had.
In our current examples,
we have the USU student. So
the first thing I'm going
to do with ETL is I'm going
to extract the data from
this USU student. It has 40
rows. And to do that, I'm
just going to indicate select.
star into,
and this will be the temp table,
a single session temp table
is initiated with the hashtag.
So here we could say temp
USU student, and we get this
data from the USU student table.
So now we're extracting all
of the data from this table.
We can obviously gather it
from different sources as well.
This appears to have run
successfully so now we can indicate
select everything from the hashtag
and then the temp USU student.
And now we have access to this to make
changes so we've extracted the data.
Okay let's go in and make a quick
transformation and for our transformations
we'll typically use update or
alter table. In this case what I'd
like to do is just transform the
last name into all capital letters.
So I'm going to update
and the name of the table I'm going
to update is hashtag temp student
and we use set along with update
so we'll set equal to and in
this case we'll use the upper and
this will take our information in
the last name and create uppercase
so we've done that transformation
we can now look at our data we now
have it excellent all uppercase
and now we can transform that data
we can put it back into a table
or we could create a new table for
that. So in this case I am going
to indicate select everything into
and I'm going to call this USU
student class 2.
In this case it would
be from the temp table.
So we've transformed the data and
now we're going to load it into
either the original table or a
new table and we've done that.
And so now we have a permanent
table called USU student class 2.
And now we have our
either our existing table
updated or a new table
created permanently
with our data transformed. So
we've extracted, transformed,
and loaded that data. In your
project some questions will
require you to use temp data.
If you prefer to use temp data
throughout all of the data
wrangling, that's fine as well.
As I mentioned just a few minutes
ago, throughout the data wrangling,
you'll be using some techniques
that we used in the OLTP module.
You may want to go back
and review some slides for
that module. We also have
that animation on OLTP.
Here's just a brief
review. We have the slides,
but this is how you
would update the data.
This is how you can alter a
table. You can either drop a
column or add a column. Just as
a reminder, when we have drop,
we use the word column, but
when we add, we don't use
column. We simply indicate the
column and then the data type.
And then finally, during the data
wrangling, we will use case expressions.
And if you remember, a case expression
is where we temporarily create
an extra column. That's how we've
been using it or the order by.
And in that case, it's
temporary and it goes away.
If you look at the code on the
screen, this is a simple case
expression because we have
case state. We have when then
and that would create a regular
case expression. If you want
to make it permanent think
about how you would do that and
You would combine some of the
OLTP with our case expressions
So here we have our basic
case expression here We
have the opportunity to make
it permanent. So what I've
done is I've created a new
column called full state and
Now we can update the
student table. We can set
full state So this is
currently has nothing in it,
and the full state is
based on a case expression.
So when case state, if it's MT, then
it's Montana, when it's Florida.
And then when this case
expression is done, because
we used an update statement,
it's no longer a temporary
column, but this is how
you can create a permanent
column data based on a
case expression. Best of
luck on the data wrangling
project. Now go get them.